<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bias on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/tags/bias/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bias on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/bias/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Normalization results in regression to the mean</title>
      <link>/2019/10/normalization-results-in-regression-to-the-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/normalization-results-in-regression-to-the-mean/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr Standard procedure in labs is to normalize values from gels/blots/etc by some standard that is expected to be constant across treatments. A problem with this is regression to the mean, which results in inflated Type I error. This means t-tests and such are too liberal, that is, we reject the null to often, or we conclude “an effect exists” when the evidence doesn’t favor this conclusion too often. The correct was to achieve the same goals as normalization is a linear model with the reference value as a covariate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the bias in the estimation of an effect given an omitted interaction term?</title>
      <link>/2019/07/what-is-bias-in-the-estimation-of-an-effect-giving-an-omitted-interaction-term/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/what-is-bias-in-the-estimation-of-an-effect-giving-an-omitted-interaction-term/</guid>
      <description>Some background (due to Sewall Wright’s method of path analysis) Given a generating model:
\[\begin{equation} y = \beta_0 + \beta_1 x_1 + \beta_2 x_2 + \beta_3 x_3 \end{equation}\] where \(x_3 = x_1 x_2\); that is, it is an interaction variable.
The total effect of \(x_1\) on \(y\) is \(\beta_1 + \frac{\mathrm{COV}(x_1, x_2)}{\mathrm{VAR}(x_1)} \beta_2 + \frac{\mathrm{COV}(x_1, x_3)}{\mathrm{VAR}(x_1)} \beta_3\).
If \(x_3\) (the interaction) is missing, its component on the total efffect is added to the coefficient of \(x_1\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bias in pre-post designs -- An example from the Turnbaugh et al (2006) mouse fecal transplant study</title>
      <link>/2018/03/bias-in-pre-post-designs-an-example-from-the-turnbaugh-et-al-2006-mouse-fecal-transplant-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/bias-in-pre-post-designs-an-example-from-the-turnbaugh-et-al-2006-mouse-fecal-transplant-study/</guid>
      <description>This post is motivated by a twitter link to a recent blog post critical of the old but influential study An obesity-associated gut microbiome with increased capacity for energy harvest with impressive citation metrics. In the post, Matthew Dalby smartly used the available data to reconstruct the final weights of the two groups. He showed these final weights were nearly the same, which is not good evidence for a treatment effect, given that the treatment was randomized among groups.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>