<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Model Averaged Coefficients on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/tags/model-averaged-coefficients/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Model Averaged Coefficients on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/model-averaged-coefficients/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On model-averaging regression coefficients</title>
      <link>/2018/05/on-model-averaging-regression-coefficients/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/on-model-averaging-regression-coefficients/</guid>
      <description>A partial regression coefficient \(b_{j.k}\) is a difference in conditional means – it is the difference in the mean response between two groups that vary in \(x_j\) by one unit but have the same values for all other covariates (\(X_k\)). The partial regression coefficient \(b_{j.k}\) estimates two parameters. The first is the regression (conditional effect) parameter, a descriptive parameter describing the population difference in conditional means
The second is the effect parameter, or Average Causal Effect, which is the direct, generating or causal effect of \(X_j\) on \(Y\), and variously defined as</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model-averaged coefficients of a GLM</title>
      <link>/2018/05/model-averaged-coefficients-of-a-glm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/model-averaged-coefficients-of-a-glm/</guid>
      <description>This is a very quick post as a comment to the statement
“For linear models, predicting from a parameter-averaged model is mathematically identical to averaging predictions, but this is not the case for non-linear models…For non-linear models, such as GLMs with log or logit link functions g(x)1, such coefficient averaging is not equivalent to prediction averaging.”
from the supplement of Dormann et al. Model averaging in ecology: a review of Bayesian, information‐theoretic and tactical approaches for predictive inference.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>