<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>P Values on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/tags/p-values/</link>
    <description>Recent content in P Values on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/p-values/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the power to test an interaction effect less than that for a main effect?</title>
      <link>/2019/07/is-the-power-to-test-an-interaction-effect-less-than-that-for-a-main-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/is-the-power-to-test-an-interaction-effect-less-than-that-for-a-main-effect/</guid>
      <description>I was googling around and somehow landed on a page that stated “When effect coding is used, statistical power is the same for all regression coefficients of the same size, whether they correspond to main effects or interactions, and irrespective of the order of the interaction”. Really? How could this be? The p-value for an interaction effect is the same regardless of dummy or effects coding, and the power of the interaction effect is less than that of the main effects even if they have the same magnitude, so my intuition said this statement must be wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GLM vs. t-tests vs. non-parametric tests if all we care about is NHST -- Update</title>
      <link>/2019/05/glm-vs-t-tests-vs-non-parametric-tests-if-all-we-care-about-is-nhst-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/glm-vs-t-tests-vs-non-parametric-tests-if-all-we-care-about-is-nhst-update/</guid>
      <description>Update to the earlier post, which was written in response to my own thinking about how to teach stastics to experimental biologists working in fields that are dominated by hypothesis testing instead of estimation. That is, should these researchers learn GLMs or is a t-test on raw or log-transformed data on something like count data good enough – or even superior? My post was written without the benefit of either [Ives](Ives, Anthony R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should we be skeptical of a &#34;large&#34; effect size if p &gt; 0.05?</title>
      <link>/2019/05/should-we-be-skeptical-of-a-large-effect-size-if-p-0-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/05/should-we-be-skeptical-of-a-large-effect-size-if-p-0-05/</guid>
      <description>Motivator: A twitter comment “Isn’t the implication that the large effect size is a direct byproduct of the lack of power? i.e. that if the the study had more power, the effect size would have been found to be smaller.”1 2
A thought: our belief in the magnitude of an observed effect should be based on our priors, which, hopefully, are formed from good mechanistic models and not sample size“.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The statistical significance filter</title>
      <link>/2019/04/the-statistical-significance-filter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/the-statistical-significance-filter/</guid>
      <description>1 Why reported effect sizes are inflated 2 Setup 3 Exploration 1 4 Unconditional means, power, and sign error 5 Conditional means 5.1 filter = 0.05 5.2 filter = 0.2    1 Why reported effect sizes are inflated This post is motivated by many discussions in Gelman’s blog but start here
When we estimate an effect1, the estimate will be a little inflated or a little diminished relative to the true effect but the expectation of the effect is the true effect.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Textbook error 101 -- A low p-value for the full model does not mean that the model is a good predictor of the response</title>
      <link>/2018/09/a-low-p-value-for-the-full-model-does-not-mean-that-the-model-is-a-good-predictor-of-the-response/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/a-low-p-value-for-the-full-model-does-not-mean-that-the-model-is-a-good-predictor-of-the-response/</guid>
      <description>On page 606, of Lock et al “Statistics: Unlocking the Power of Data”, the authors state in item D “The p-value from the ANOVA table is 0.000 so the model as a whole is effective at predicting grade point average.” Ah no.
library(data.table) library(mvtnorm) rho &amp;lt;- 0.5 n &amp;lt;- 10^5 Sigma &amp;lt;- diag(2) Sigma[1,2] &amp;lt;- Sigma[2,1] &amp;lt;- rho X &amp;lt;- rmvnorm(n, mean=c(0,0), sigma=Sigma) colnames(X) &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;X1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;X2&amp;quot;) beta &amp;lt;- c(0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the range of reasonable P-values given a two standard error difference in means?</title>
      <link>/2018/03/what-is-the-range-of-reasonable-p-values-given-a-two-standard-error-difference-in-means/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/what-is-the-range-of-reasonable-p-values-given-a-two-standard-error-difference-in-means/</guid>
      <description>Here is the motivating quote for this post, from Andrew Gelman’s blog post “Five ways to fix statistics”
 I agree with just about everything in Leek’s article except for this statement: “It’s also impractical to say that statistical metrics such as P values should not be used to make decisions. Sometimes a decision (editorial or funding, say) must be made, and clear guidelines are useful.” Yes, decisions need to be made, but to suggest that p-values be used to make editorial or funding decisions—that’s just horrible.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>