<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Categorical X on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/tags/categorical-x/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Categorical X on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/categorical-x/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the power to test an interaction effect less than that for a main effect?</title>
      <link>/2019/07/is-the-power-to-test-an-interaction-effect-less-than-that-for-a-main-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/is-the-power-to-test-an-interaction-effect-less-than-that-for-a-main-effect/</guid>
      <description>I was googling around and somehow landed on a page that stated “When effect coding is used, statistical power is the same for all regression coefficients of the same size, whether they correspond to main effects or interactions, and irrespective of the order of the interaction”. Really? How could this be? The p-value for an interaction effect is the same regardless of dummy or effects coding, and the power of the interaction effect is less than that of the main effects even if they have the same magnitude, so my intuition said this statement must be wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Covariate adjustment in randomized experiments</title>
      <link>/2019/04/covariate-adjustment-in-randomized-experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/covariate-adjustment-in-randomized-experiments/</guid>
      <description>The post motivated by a tweetorial from Darren Dahly
In an experiment, do we adjust for covariates that differ between treatment levels measured pre-experiment (“imbalance” in random assignment), where a difference is inferred from a t-test with p &amp;lt; 0.05? Or do we adjust for all covariates, regardless of differences pre-test? Or do we adjust only for covariates that have sustantial correlation with the outcome? Or do we not adjust at all?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interaction plots with ggplot2</title>
      <link>/2018/10/interaction-plots-with-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/10/interaction-plots-with-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>ggpubr is a fantastic resource for teaching applied biostats because it makes ggplot a bit easier for students. I’m not super familiar with all that ggpubr can do, but I’m not sure it includes a good “interaction plot” function. Maybe I’m wrong. But if I’m not, here is a simple function to create a gg_interaction plot.
The gg_interaction function returns a ggplot of the modeled means and standard errors and not the raw means and standard errors computed from each group independently.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>