<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R Doodles</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>When do we introduce best statistical practices to undergraduate biology majors? Part 1. Bar plot alternatives</title>
      <link>/2018/03/when-do-we-introduce-best-statistical-practices-to-undergraduate-biology-majors-part-1-bar-plot-alternatives/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/when-do-we-introduce-best-statistical-practices-to-undergraduate-biology-majors-part-1-bar-plot-alternatives/</guid>
      <description>Within the cell biology/physiology literature, but not so much the ecology and evolution literature, there have been several editorials and short papers encouraging researchers to use alternatives to bar plots to communicate experimental results (here, here, here, here, and here).
Bar plots aren’t wrong, there are simply much better plots for communicating features of our data or the models that we fit. All the links above advocate some version of box plots or dot plots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bias in pre-post designs -- An example from the Turnbaugh et al (2006) mouse fecal transplant study</title>
      <link>/2018/03/bias-in-pre-post-designs-an-example-from-the-turnbaugh-et-al-2006-mouse-fecal-transplant-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/bias-in-pre-post-designs-an-example-from-the-turnbaugh-et-al-2006-mouse-fecal-transplant-study/</guid>
      <description>This post is motivated by a twitter link to a recent blog post critical of the old but influential study An obesity-associated gut microbiome with increased capacity for energy harvest with impressive citation metrics. In the post, Matthew Dalby smartly used the available data to reconstruct the final weights of the two groups. He showed these final weights were nearly the same, which is not good evidence for a treatment effect, given that the treatment was randomized among groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is an R doodle?</title>
      <link>/2018/03/what-is-an-r-doodle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/what-is-an-r-doodle/</guid>
      <description>An R doodle is a short script to check intuition or understanding. Almost always, this involves generating fake data. I might create an R doodle when I’m reviewing a manuscript or reading a published paper and I want to check if their statistical analysis is doing what the authors think it is doing. Or maybe I create it to help me figure out what the authors are doing. Or I might be teaching some method and I create an R doodle to help me understand how the method behaves given different input (fake) data sets.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>