<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reproducibility on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/categories/reproducibility/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reproducibility on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/reproducibility/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Normalization results in regression to the mean</title>
      <link>/2019/10/normalization-results-in-regression-to-the-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/normalization-results-in-regression-to-the-mean/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr Standard procedure in labs is to normalize values from gels/blots/etc by some standard that is expected to be constant across treatments. A problem with this is regression to the mean, which results in inflated Type I error. This means t-tests and such are too liberal, that is, we reject the null to often, or we conclude “an effect exists” when the evidence doesn’t favor this conclusion too often. The correct was to achieve the same goals as normalization is a linear model with the reference value as a covariate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reanalyzing data from Human Gut Microbiota from Autism Spectrum Disorder Promote Behavioral Symptoms in Mice</title>
      <link>/2019/06/reanalyzing-data-from-human-gut-microbiota-from-autism-spectrum-disorder-promote-behavioral-symptoms-in-mice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/06/reanalyzing-data-from-human-gut-microbiota-from-autism-spectrum-disorder-promote-behavioral-symptoms-in-mice/</guid>
      <description>Update - This post has been updated
A very skeletal analysis of
Sharon, G., Cruz, N.J., Kang, D.W., Gandal, M.J., Wang, B., Kim, Y.M., Zink, E.M., Casey, C.P., Taylor, B.C., Lane, C.J. and Bramer, L.M., 2019. Human Gut Microbiota from Autism Spectrum Disorder Promote Behavioral Symptoms in Mice. Cell, 177(6), pp.1600-1618.
which got some attention on pubpeer.
Commenters are questioning the result of Fig1G. It is very hard to infer a p-value from plots like these, where the data are multi-level, regardless of if means and some kind of error bar is presented.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>