<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pre Post on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/tags/pre-post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pre Post on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/pre-post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing longitudinal data -- a simple pre-post design</title>
      <link>/2020/03/analyzing-longitudinal-data-a-simple-pre-post-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/analyzing-longitudinal-data-a-simple-pre-post-design/</guid>
      <description>A skeletal response to a twitter question:
“ANOVA (time point x group) or ANCOVA (group with time point as a covariate) for intervention designs? Discuss.”
follow-up “Only 2 time points in this case (pre- and post-intervention), and would wanna basically answer the question of whether out of the 3 intervention groups, some improve on measure X more than others after the intervention”
Here I compare five methods using fake pre-post data, including</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bias in pre-post designs -- An example from the Turnbaugh et al (2006) mouse fecal transplant study</title>
      <link>/2018/03/bias-in-pre-post-designs-an-example-from-the-turnbaugh-et-al-2006-mouse-fecal-transplant-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/bias-in-pre-post-designs-an-example-from-the-turnbaugh-et-al-2006-mouse-fecal-transplant-study/</guid>
      <description>This post is motivated by a twitter link to a recent blog post critical of the old but influential study An obesity-associated gut microbiome with increased capacity for energy harvest with impressive citation metrics. In the post, Matthew Dalby smartly used the available data to reconstruct the final weights of the two groups. He showed these final weights were nearly the same, which is not good evidence for a treatment effect, given that the treatment was randomized among groups.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>