<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Anova on R Doodles</title>
    <link>/tags/anova/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Anova on R Doodles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/anova/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimate of marginal (&#34;main&#34;) effects instead of ANOVA for factorial experiments</title>
      <link>/2019/11/estimate-of-marginal-main-effects-instead-of-anova-for-factorial-experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/11/estimate-of-marginal-main-effects-instead-of-anova-for-factorial-experiments/</guid>
      <description>Comparing marginal effects to main effect terms in an ANOVA table First, some fake data Comparison of marginal effects vs. “main” effects term of ANOVA table when data are balanced Comparison of marginal effects vs. “main” effects term of ANOVA table when data are unbalanced  When to estimate marginal effects   keywords: estimation, ANOVA, factorial, model reduction, conditional effects, marginal effects
This doodle has two parts. In part one, I compare the inference from the estimation of marginal effects of a factorial design to inference from the “main” effects of an ANOVA table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the power to test an interaction effect less than that for a main effect?</title>
      <link>/2019/07/is-the-power-to-test-an-interaction-effect-less-than-that-for-a-main-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/is-the-power-to-test-an-interaction-effect-less-than-that-for-a-main-effect/</guid>
      <description>I was googling around and somehow landed on a page that stated “When effect coding is used, statistical power is the same for all regression coefficients of the same size, whether they correspond to main effects or interactions, and irrespective of the order of the interaction”. Really? How could this be? The p-value for an interaction effect is the same regardless of dummy or effects coding, and, with dummy coding (R’s default), the power of the interaction effect is less than that of the coefficients for the main factors when they have the same magnitude, so my intuition said this statement must be wrong.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>